Guide to the Nicholas B. Scheetz Collection, approximately 9th-18th century
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Nicholas B. Scheetz Collection
approximately 9th-18th century
Scheetz, Nicholas B.
1.6 cubic feet (5 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Leaves, fragments, and codices of manuscripts, some illuminated, primarily in Latin, from a variety of sources. Collection includes one printed item from the late 15th century and one stenciled item from the 18th century.
Scope and Content Note
Collection includes sermons, bibles, devotional books, music, liturgical manuscripts, literary manuscripts, and notarial and financial records. The material originates from a range of geographic areas including Italy, England, the Netherlands, France, Spain, and Armenia. A substantial number of items date from the 16th century.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
The English Documents Collection includes items dating from 1552 on.
The Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection includes items dating from the 11th to 17th century.
Subject Headings
Names:
Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, approximately 4 B.C.-65 A.D.
Organizations:
Catholic Church--Liturgy; Catholic Church--Prayers and devotions
Titles:
Bible
Subjects:
Illumination of books and manuscripts, Gothic; Manuscripts, Armenian; Manuscripts, Latin (Medieval and modern); Manuscripts, Medieval; Sermons, Latin
Document Types:
Account books; Antiphonaries; Books of hours; Breviaries; Choir books; Graduals; Illuminated manuscripts; Missals; Passionals; Processionals; Psalters
VCL Categories:
Medieval and Early Modern Manuscripts; Printing and Publishing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, March 2019. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, April 2023-February 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Vassar College alumna, Diana Pearson (VC 1978). The manuscripts and codices were collected by Pearson’s late husband, Nicholas B. Scheetz, Manuscript Curator at Georgetown University.
Container List
- Peter the Chanter (d. 1197), Summa Abel [France], early 13th century (Scheetz MS 1)
- A Leaf from John Wyclif (d. 1384), Quadraginta sermones de tempore, on paper [England], late 14th or early 15th century (Scheetz MS 2, Folder (Folder 1.01))
- An Incomplete Book of Hours, in Latin with some Netherlandish [Netherlands (diocese of Utrecht)], 15th century (Scheetz MS 3)
- A Portion of a Book of Hours, of Unidentified Use [France], late 15th and early 16th centuries (Scheetz MS 4)
- A Leaf from a Book of Hours [France], 15th century (Scheetz MS 5, Folder (Folder 1.02))
- Portions of a Psalter [England], early 15th century (Scheetz MS 6)
- Portion of a Breviary, Use of Paris [France], 15th century (Scheetz MS 7)
- Gradual for Advent and Christmas [Netherlands (Brussels area?)], circa 1450-1499 (Scheetz MS 8)
- Two Consecutive Bifolia from an Augustinian(?) Gradual [Spain], 16th (or 17th?) century (Scheetz MS 9, Folder (Oversize Folder 3.01))
- A Leaf from a miniature Processional [France (Paris or Poissy?)], 16th century (Scheetz MS 10, Folder (Folder 1.03))
- Three leaves from a Processional(?) [France (Normandy or Caen?)], 15th century; [See also Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection, Item 8 ] (Scheetz MS 11a-11c, Folder (Folder 1.04))
- A Leaf from a Choir Breviary [Italy], 16th century (Scheetz MS 12, Folder (Oversize Folder 3.02))
- A Cutting of an illuminated initial from a Choirbook [Italy (probably northeast)], 1475-1499 (Scheetz MS 13, Folder (Folder 1.05))
- A Leaf from a Bible [France (not Paris?)], 1250-1275 (Scheetz MS 14, Folder (Folder 1.06))
- Eleven Leaves from a Pocket Bible [England (probably Oxford)], 1250-1275 (Scheetz MS 15)
- A Leaf from the Franciscan “Goodspeed Bible” [Italy (Umbria, probably Perugia)], 14th century (Scheetz MS 16, Folder (Folder 1.07))
- A Bifolium from Peter Lombard, Great Gloss on the Pauline Epistles [France (Paris?)], 13th century (first quarter?) (Scheetz MS 17, Folder (Folder 2.01))
- A Leaf from a Breviary [Italy], 15th century (Scheetz MS 18, Folder (Folder 1.08))
- A Leaf from a Cistercian(?) Breviary [France], 1250-1299 (Scheetz MS 19, Folder (Folder 1.09))
- A Fragment of a Missal [Germany], late 13th or 14th century (Scheetz MS 20, Folder (Folder 1.10))
- Two leaves of a Passionary or Martyrology [Spain (Léon?)], 12th century (mid- or second half) (Scheetz MS 21a-21b, Folder (Oversize Folder 3.03))
- A Fragment of Martianus Capella, On the Marriage of Philology and Mercury, with interlinear and marginal glosses [France], circa 1100-1125 (Scheetz MS 22, Folder (Folder 1.11))
- A Fragment of Seneca the Elder, Controversiae [Germany], circa 850-899 (Scheetz MS 23, Folder (Folder 1.12))
- Two fragments of a Register concerning the Recruitment and Payment of Mercenaries, in Latin with some Italian [Italy (Florence)], circa 1368 (Scheetz MS 24a-24b, Folder (Folder 1.13))
- Notary’s book of Anthoine de Toulouse [France (South, Toulouse region?)], 1517 (Scheetz MS 25)
- Three leaves from the Summer part of the Sanctorale of a Gradual [Spain], 17th century (after 1622) (Scheetz MS 26a-26c, Folder (Oversize Folder 3.04))
- A Leaf from “The St Albans Bible” [France (Paris)], circa 1330-1339 (Scheetz MS 27, Folder (Folder 1.14))
- A Leaf from “The Bohun Bible” [England (East Anglia, perhaps Cambridge?)], mid-14th century (Scheetz MS 28, Folder (Folder 2.02))
- Five Leaves from a Homilary, in Armenian [Iran (Isfahan)], 1671-1672; [See also Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection, Items 52-53 ] (Scheetz MS 29a-29e, Folder (Oversize Folder 3.05))
- A Leaf of a Choir Psalter [Spain (Toledo?)], [17th century?] (Scheetz MS 30, Folder (Oversize Folder 5.01))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1545 Nov 5 (Scheetz MS 31, Folder (Oversize Folder 3.06))
- Document [Italy (Aquileia)], 1542 Nov 22 (Scheetz MS 32, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.01))
- Document [Italy], 1531 Feb 7 (Scheetz MS 33, Folder (Folder 2.03))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1577 Nov 11 (Scheetz MS 34, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.02))
- Deed of Sale [Italy (Udine)], 1546 Aug 25 (Scheetz MS 35, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.03))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1525 Feb 27 (Scheetz MS 36, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.04))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1560 Dec 24 (Scheetz MS 37, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.05))
- Deed of Sale, notary public Blasius [Italy (Maniago)], 1563 Oct 16 (Scheetz MS 38, Folder (Folder 1.15))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1571 May 11 (Scheetz MS 39, Folder (Folder 2.04))
- Document [Italy (Spilimbergo)], 1552 Jun 19 (Scheetz MS 40, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.06))
- Document [Italy (Spilimbergo)], 1578 Jan 25 (Scheetz MS 41, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.07))
- Two leaves from a printed edition of Seneca the Younger, Epistolae morales, on paper [Italy (Treviso)], 1478 (Scheetz MS 42, Folder (Folder 2.05))
- Document [Italy ("Villa Arzenatti")], 1453 Jun 26 (Scheetz MS 43, Folder (Folder 2.06))
- Document [Italy (Spilimbergo)], 1576 Sep 9 (Scheetz MS 44, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.08))
- Confirmation of the legitimacy of Juan Arias Portocarrero as Second Count of Puñonrostro [Italy (Rome)], circa 1581-1585 (Scheetz MS 45, Folder (Folder 1.16))
- A Leaf from Seneca the Younger, Epistolae morales [Italy (perhaps Rome)], circa 1470 (Scheetz MS 46, Folder (Folder 1.17))
- A Leaf from a Book of Hours [France], late 14th century (Scheetz MS 47, Folder (Folder 1.18))
- A Leaf from a Psalter [Southern Netherlands (Flanders)], circa 1250-1299 (Scheetz MS 48, Folder (Folder 1.19))
- A Leaf from the Temporale of a Gradual [Spain], [17th century?] (Scheetz MS 49, Folder (Oversize Folder 4.09))
- Two Leaves from the Sanctorale of a stenciled Gradual [South America (or Spain?)], [17th or 18th century?] (Scheetz MS 50, Folder (Oversize Folder 5.02))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1525 Nov 3 (Scheetz MS 51, Folder (Folder 1.20))
- Deed of Sale [Italy (Spilimbergo)], 1532 Aug 22 (Scheetz MS 52, Folder (Folder 1.21))
- Deed of Sale [Italy (Maniago)], 1544 Oct 13 (Scheetz MS 53, Folder (Folder 1.22))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1554 Nov 3 (Scheetz MS 54, Folder (Folder 1.23))
- Document [Italy], 1550 Nov 29 (Scheetz MS 55, Folder (Folder 1.24))
- Document [Italy (Spilimbergo)], 1552 Mar 8 (Scheetz MS 56, Folder (Folder 1.25))
- Deed of Sale [Italy (Tramonti di Sopra)], 1555 Apr 1 (Scheetz MS 57, Folder (Folder 1.26))
- Deed of Sale, notary public Blasius [Italy (Maniago)], 1557 Sep 10 (Scheetz MS 58, Folder (Folder 1.27))
- Deed of Sale, notary public Blasius [Italy (Maniago)], 1560 Sep 23 (Scheetz MS 59, Folder (Folder 1.28))
- Deed of Sale, notary public Blasius [Italy (Maniago)], 1563 Aug 31 (Scheetz MS 60, Folder (Folder 1.29))
- Deed of Sale, notary public Blasius [Italy (Maniago)], 1567 Jun 30 (Scheetz MS 61, Folder (Folder 1.30))
- Document [Italy (Spilimbergo)], 1580 Jul 4 (Scheetz MS 62, Folder (Folder 1.31))
- Deed of Sale [Italy (Maniago)], 1580 Oct 3 (Scheetz MS 63, Folder (Folder 1.32))
- Deed of Sale [Italy (Maniago)], 1585 Apr 27 (Scheetz MS 64, Folder (Folder 1.33))
- Deed of Sale to Lord Pomplius and his brother Peter [Italy (Maniago)], 1586 Feb 2 or 11 (Scheetz MS 65, Folder (Folder 1.34))
- Deed of Sale from Florianus Pelligrini [Italy (Methuno?)], 1591 Aug 24 (Scheetz MS 66, Folder (Folder 1.35))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1565 Nov 6 (Scheetz MS 67, Folder (Folder 1.36))
- Document [Italy (Maniago?)], 1541 Nov 5 (Scheetz MS 68, Folder (Folder 1.37))
- Document [Italy (Maniago)], 1542 Mar 25 (Scheetz MS 69, Folder (Folder 1.38))
- Document [Italy (Spilimbergo)], 1558 Jul 25 (Scheetz MS 70, Folder (Folder 1.39))